A Guide to the Mary Holt Woolfolk Carlton Papers, 1969-1983
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Mary Holt Woolfolk Carlton Papers, 1969-1983
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 11
2.5 linear feet
Mary Holt Woolfolk Carlton
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to University Library Services in April of 1983 by Ms. Carlton.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mary Holt Woolfolk Carlton was born March 6, 1915, the daughter of Algar Woolfolk and Louise McCarthy Woolfolk. A Richmond native, she is the granddaughter of Carlton McCarthy, once mayor of Richmond.
She attended Westhampton College of the University of Richmond and received a Bachelors degree in Social Science from William and Mary in 1955 and a Masters in Social Work in 1961 from Richmond Professional Institute (now VCU). She worked as a family counselor. She was married to Louis C. Carlton.
Carlton became active in women's issues in 1969. She was a charter member and treasurer of the Virginia Women's Political Caucus and co-founded, along with Zelda Nordlinger, the Richmond Chapter of the National Organization for Women (NOW). She chaired NOW's Women in Religion National Task Force and was active in advocating increased involvement of women within the church and of elimination of sexism found in biblical literature. She was an active member of St. Paul's Episcopal Church. Carlton also served on NOW's Compliance and Enforcement Task Force and corresponded with various businesses on their employment policies regarding women. She was also a member in the Ginter Park Garden Club and the Ginter Park Woman's Club.
She participated in the integration of Thalhimer's Men's Soup Bar in August of 1970 and of the Miller & Rhoades Tea Room a year later. Throughout the 1970s, she gave speeches advocating the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment and corresponded with numerous legislators about the matter. She frequently wrote letters expressing her opinion on women's issues to both Richmond newspapers, the Richmond Times-Dispatch and Richmond News-Leader, various magazines, columnists, and broadcasters. Carlton and other activists have been credited in convincing Richmond Newspapers Inc. to end their segregation of their want-ad job classifications by gender in 1973.
Scope and Content Information
The collection documents Carlton's activities as an activist in the emerging women's movement of the 1970s and includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and other materials dating mostly from the 1970s. Much of the correspondence includes copies of the letters Carlton sent and the replies she received.
One of the most significant portions of the collection pertains to Carlton's activities, and those of other local supporters, regarding passage of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), including correspondence with fellow activists and with state and national elected officials. Various publications, from newspaper clippings and journal articles to pamphlets and leaflets, are also included in the collection.
Materials relating to Carlton's interest in the changing role of women in the church, both within the Episcopal church and in other denominations in general, is also represented. Her involvement within Richmond's St. Paul's Episcopal Church is documented and includes correspondence with controversial Episcopal Bishop John "Jack" S. Spong.
Carlton also served on NOW's Compliance and Enforcement Task Force and the collection includes correspondence between Carlton and various businesses, both locally and nationally, on their employment policies regarding women.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein.
Contents List
- Addresses, speeches and papers by Mary Holt Carlton, n.d. 1970s (Box 1)
- Addresses, speeches by Zelda Nordlinger 1969, 1970 (Box 1)
- Biographical Information on Mary Holt Carlton, n.d. 1974 (Box 1)
- Campaign material-miscellaneous, n.d. 1970s (Box 1)
- Carlton, Lewis C.-photo, clippings, n.d. (Box 1)
- Chisholm, Shirley-public forum at the Richmond Mosque 1973 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-n.d. 1970-1980 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Baliles, Gerald L. 1976 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Byrd, Harry F. 1970-1978 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Carter, Jimmy and Rosalyn-Carter White House 1976-1979 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-General Assembly members-regarding ERA 1972-1978 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Irvin, Sam 1971 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Kennedy, Edward 1973 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Landers, Ann 1971, 1980 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Letters to the editor, editorials and other news clippings, n.d. 1970-1978 (Box 1)
- Letters to the media, responses 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Letters to the media, responses 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Letters to the media, responses 1972 (Box 1)
- Letters to the media, responses 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Letters to the media, responses 1975-1980 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-McGovern, George-McGovern Campaign 1972 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Miller and Rhoads 1970-1972 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Nixon, Richard-Nixon White house 1971 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Nordlinger, Zelda K., n.d. 1970-1974 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Nordlinger, Zelda K. 1978-1979 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Post, Elizabeth L. 1972 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Satterfield, David E. (U.S. House of Representatives) 1974-1978 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-United States Congress members-regarding ERA 1971-1978 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Van Buren, Abigail (Dear Abby) 1971-1977 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Weinberger, Casper 1973 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Women's Suffrage 50th Anniversary postage stamp on envelope 1970 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Congressional Record-speeches by U.S. COngressmen on the ERA 1970s (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1973-1977 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-March and Rally 1976 (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Marching chants/songs (Box 2)
- News clippings 1970s (Box 2)
- Publications, pamphlets 1970s (Box 2)
- Report by Citizen's Advisory Council on the Status of Women 1970 (Box 2)
- Report on the Task Force on the Effect of Ratification of the ERA on the Law in Mary Virginia 1973 (Box 2)
- Virginia ERA-PAC of Henrico (Box 2)
- Correspondence-Yale Law Journal- The Equal Rights Amendment: A Constitutional Basis for Equal Rights for Women (Box 2)
- Equal Employment Opportunity Commission-Richmond Newspapers, other companies-news clippings 1971-1974 (Box 3)
- Genesis III- newsletter-Philadelphia Task Force on Women in Religion 1971-1973 (Box 3)
- Herbs and recipes, n.d. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. 1970s (Box 3)
- New clippings-Miscellaneous (1 of 3) 1970s (Box 3)
- News clippings-Miscellaneous (2 of 3) 1970s (Box 3)
- News clippings-Miscellaneous (3of 3) 1970s (Box 3)
- News clippings-Nordlinger, Zelda 1970s (Box 3)
- NOW-Ecumenical Task Force on Women and Religion, n.d. (Box 3)
- NOW-National Task Force, Women and Religion 1977 (Box 3)
- NOW-Compliance and Enforcement Task Force 1970s (Box 4)
- NOW-Newsletter/Newspaper 1970-1979 (Box 4)
- NOW-Richmond/Virginia chapter, newsletters, miscellaneous publications, n.d. 1973-1983 (Box 4)
- NOW- Strategies for Business Compliance and Government Enforcement1973 (Box 4)
- NOW- A Survey of the Washington Post Newspaper, Washington, D.C. (Box 4)
- Publications-How to Erase Sex Discrimination in Vocational Education 1977 (Box 4)
- Publications-Miscellaneous, n.d. 1970s (Box 4)
- Publications- Sexual Barrier: Legal and Economic Aspects of Employment-supplement 1 and 2 1971-1972 (Box 4)
- Publications- Status of Women-report, Virginia Commonwealth on the Status of Women 1971 (Box 4)
- Publications-Women's issues-various publications, n.d. 1970s (Box 5)
- Richmond Women's Center- Woman's Page, flier,n.d. 1970s (Box 5)
- St. Pauls Episcopal Church-Cheek, Alison M.-correspondence, news clipping 1972, 1975 (Box 5)
- St. Pauls Episcopal Church-Church fliers and programs 1972, 1974, 1980 (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Consultation on Women in Theological Education Union Theological (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Seminary course material 1973 (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Correspondence 1970-1976 (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Episcopal Women's Caucus 1976-1978 (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Notes, n.d. (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Religious publications, news clippings, n.d.l 1970s (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Spiritual Celebration 1978-1980 (Box 5)
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church-Sprong, John S.-correspondence, miscellaneous, n.d. 1971-1979 (Box 5)
- Social Work-correspondence, publications, n.d. 1974-1976 (Box 5)
- Social Work-Miscellaneous 1970s (Box 5)
- Sexism in children's Literature-correspondence,n.d. 1972-1976 (Box 6)
- Sexism in children's Literature-Council on Inter-Racial Books for Children 1975 (Box 6)
- Sexism in children's Literature-News clippings, n.d. 1970s (Box 6)
- Sexism in children's Literature-Publications, catalogs, n.d. 1970s (Box 6)
- Report- Sex Role Stereotyping in church School Curricula1972 (Box 6)
- Spokeswoman, The (An independent monthly newsletter of women's news) n.d. 1971-1973, 1977 (Box 6)
- Virginia General Assembly-miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Virginia Women's Political Caucus-correspondence and miscellaneous, n.d. 1971-1974 (Box 6)
- Virginia Women's Political Caucus-Handbook 1972 (Box 6)
- Virginia Women's Political Caucus-National Women's Political Caucus-convention 1973 (Box 6)
- Voter Identification Card-Carlton, Mary W. 1975 (Box 6)
- The Women Activist (a Virginia publication), n.d. 1971-1973 (Box 6)
- Women's Rights of Richmond-Correspondence, newsletter, miscellaneous, n.d. 1970-1972 (Box 6)